<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>England's preservation or, a sermon discovering the onely way to prevent destroying judgements: preached to the Honourable House of Commons at their last solemne fast, being on May, 25. 1642. By Obadiah Sedgwicke Batchelour in Divinity and minister of Coggeshall in Essex. Published by order of that house.</title>
            <author>Sedgwick, Obadiah, 1600?-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92852</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2372</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E150_22</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212706</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871291</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871291</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156756</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92852)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156756)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 27:E150[22])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>England's preservation or, a sermon discovering the onely way to prevent destroying judgements: preached to the Honourable House of Commons at their last solemne fast, being on May, 25. 1642. By Obadiah Sedgwicke Batchelour in Divinity and minister of Coggeshall in Essex. Published by order of that house.</title>
                  <author>Sedgwick, Obadiah, 1600?-1658.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. B. for Samuel Gellibrand, at the Brazen Serpent in Pauls Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In two parts.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached at the late fast, before the Commons house of Parliament.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank. -- Cf. Jeffs. English Revolution, v.3, p.3.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Jeremiah IV, 3 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156756:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>England's PRESERVATION OR, A SERMON diſcovering the onely way to prevent deſtroying JUDGEMENTS: Preached to the Honourable HOUSE of COMMONS at their laſt ſolemne Faſt, being on <hi>May,</hi> 25. 1642.</p>
            <p>BY OBADIAH SEDGWICKE Batchelour in Divinity and Miniſter of COGGESHALL in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Published by Order of that Houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>JEREMIAH 13. 27.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Hieruſalem wilt thou not be made cleane? When ſhall it once be?</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. B.</hi> for <hi>Samuel Gellibrand,</hi> at the Brazen Serpent in <hi>Pauls</hi> CHURCH-Yard. 1642.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:156756:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156756:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable Houſe of Commons aſſembled in <hi>PARLIAMENT.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Sermon which I preached by your command, and you harkned unto with much acceptance, and is now printed by our Order, I moſt humbly preſent unto your Gracious Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, and Religious practice; It hath this only in it; that it is ſeaſonable; what one once writ to <hi>Aegidius</hi> the Abbot of <hi>Norinberg</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Davids</hi> words in <hi>Pſalme</hi> 118. They are <hi>verba vivenda, non legenda:</hi> That may be affirm'd of the Text I preached on, the pith and matter of it ſhould be lived, and not heard only: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance is a living word: <hi>Alexander</hi> (as <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Orat. 1. de Alex. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> reports) demanded of <hi>Porus</hi> (whom he had ſurpriſed) what his thoughts were of him, he anſwered, I thinke of <hi>Alexander, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galiter,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:156756:3"/>
and thats enough ſaid hee, for in that word all other things are contained: the ſame I may ſay, if any man demands what our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and diſtracted Kingdome ſhould doe? I anſwer, <hi>Repent,</hi> and in that word (if lived and done) all our ſafeties and hopes are contained.</p>
            <p>There were 3. things (moſt Honourable Sirs!) which <hi>Luther</hi> did feare would prove <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Melchior Adam: in vita Luther:</hi> p. 157. 158.</note> to bee the Ruine of Religion. 1. Oblivion. 2 Security. 3. Carnall policy: The good <hi>God</hi> overthrow theſe in our Land, leaſt our land be overthrowne by theſe: Though Miniſters diſcover all ſorts of ſins, and though a <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> diſcovers all ſorts of plots and dangers, yet people are ſetled on their Lee's, they will not ſee, nor feare, nor humble themſelves, nor turne to the Lord at all; <hi>O pray,</hi> (ſaid a dying man in the beginning of the <hi>German</hi> reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) that God would preſerve the Goſpell <hi>(pontifex enim Romanus, &amp; Concilium Trident. mira moliuntur)</hi> For the Pope and Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> are hatching of ſtrange things: Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſay as much and more to people, pray, be humbled, reform; For you ſee what the blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die Papiſts have done in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and you heare what they are plotting againſt <hi>England,</hi> we do thus
<pb facs="tcp:156756:3"/>
ſpeak and weepe, but man will not hearken and obey; They who will not eaſily ſee their ſins, will as hardly beleeve their dangers: <hi>Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, fuge Brenti! cito, citius, citiſsime,</hi> ſo friendly did a <hi>Senatour</hi> of <hi>Hala</hi> adviſe <hi>Brentius,</hi> haſt, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten, make all the haſt you can, your life is loſt elſe: He embraced the adviſe, &amp; preſerved his life by it; O that Gods adviſes (ſo frequent, ſo earneſt, ſo and more ſafe) to humbling and reforming might once bee regarded and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed: we ſhall never be ſafe, if wee ever remaine impenitent.</p>
            <p>As for your ſelves, Honourable Sirs! wee have all cauſe to bleſſe God for the worthy Acts already done by you, and for your further intentions of moſt excellent good to our Church and Kingdom; Ripen theſe intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (wee pray you) into Actions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That our Church may be glorious, and our State ſafe; and both flouriſhing and ſtable: good actions are excellent, though evill men oppoſe them, nor ſhal they be therfore, the leſſe ſucceſſeful: remember that Chriſt hath conquerd all the world, and a world conquerd by Chriſt ſhall never be able to conquer truth.</p>
            <p>I have one requeſt which I earneſtly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb facs="tcp:156756:4"/>
to your ſelves and the Houſe of Lords, It is onely this, Haſten (what you can) <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> Reformation, and <hi>Irelands</hi> preſervation: In theſe the good and Almighty God unite, ſtrengthen, protect, and proſper you All, To whoſe everlaſting armes, you and all your pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous endeavours are commended by your dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Oratour.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Obadiah Sedwicke.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Die Mercurij 25. May 1642.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <p>IT is this day Ordered by the Commons now Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in <hi>Parliament</hi> that Maſter <hi>Harris,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Obadiah Sedgwicke,</hi> who this day, being the day of the publike Faſt, at the intreaty of the ſaid Commons; preached at Saint <hi>Margaret Weſtminſter,</hi> ſhall have thankes returned them, for the great and worthy paines they have taken, and that they bee deſired to print their Sermons, and that no man preſume to print them, but ſuch as they ſhall appoint, till the Houſe ſhall take further Order.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. Elſyng Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>I appoint <hi>Samuell Gellibrand</hi> to print my Sermon.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Obadiah Sedgwick.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:156756:4"/>
            <head>A Sermon Preached at the late <hi>Fast,</hi> to the Commons Houſe OF PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>JEREM. 4. 3.</bibl>
               <q>Thus ſaith the Lord to the men of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> breake up your fallow ground, and ſow not among Thornes.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is a learned writer who ſpeakes of foure dayes for a ſinner. <note place="margin">Bernard.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt is <hi>Dies Faetoris,</hi> A day of loathſomeneſſe, <note place="margin">4. Dayes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to man.</note> and this is the time when the ſinner lies rotting in the grave of ſin. 2. The ſecond <hi>Dies Timoris,</hi> a day of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, and this is the time when Conſcience begins
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:156756:5"/>
to bee awakened with the ſight and ſenſe of ſinne; 3. The third is <hi>Dies Doloris,</hi> a day of mourning, and this is the time when the heart begins to melt into Teares for ſinning; The fourth is <hi>Dies Laboris,</hi> a day of Combat, and this is the time when the penitent and converted ſoule ſets it ſelfe againſt the temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſin.</p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe is the worſt of our dayes, and yet too common (the dead in this ſenſe are more than the living.) The ſecond of theſe is a bitter and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent day, and yet it may prove happie and cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full (there being more hope of a ſore Conſcience then of a ſeared Conſcience) The two laſt are (like precious Jewels) very good, but very Rare: It is an eaſie thing to finde ſinners, but it is not an eaſie thing to finde mourning ſinners, and penitent ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</p>
            <p>So blinde is the minde of man, ſo perverſe is the will of a ſinner, ſo prevalent is the love of ſinne, ſo deſperate is the reſolution of an hardned heart, that neither the Golden Scepter, nor the Iron Rod, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſweeteſt mercies, nor the ſharpeſt miſeries will eaſily prevaile with ſinning man, to become a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent man; But though God be leaving, though mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies be ſetting, though wrath be approaching, though life be ſhort, though hell be fearefull, yet it is a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand to one, but the ſinner remaines (under all theſe) conſtantly wicked, or onely deceitfully good.</p>
            <p>A cleare inſtance whereof, you have in the <hi>Iewes</hi> in this Chapter, who notwithſtanding they had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſinned away their God, their Country, their lives, their helpes, their hopes; And notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all their warnings by variety of Prophets, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:156756:5"/>
all their ſufferings by variety of puniſhments, and all their threatnings in variety of Judgments, though there was but a ſtep twixt them and death, only one mercy twixt them &amp; utter deſtruction by the enemy, yet either they totally neglected the worke, or would not bee perſwaded throughly to act the duty of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
            <p>The Lord ſaw this dangerous obſtinacy and pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties it, and ſtrives with them to ſave their ſoules, that they might (by this meanes) ſave their Countrey. The way he ſpreads before them is expreſſed,</p>
            <p>Partly in verſe 1. <hi>[If thou wilt Returne, O Iſrael! ſaith the Lord, Returne unto me, and if thou wilt put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thine abominations out of my ſight, then thou ſhalt not Remove:] q. d.</hi> leave thy ſinnes and ſave all. Thou haſt made many overtures and ſemblances thereof by Faſtings, by confeſſings, by prayings. Adde now one thing more, Repent in good earneſt. This will bee life to your ſolemnities and ſafetie to your Nation.</p>
            <p>Partly in ver. 3. <hi>[Break up your fallow ground and ſow not among thornes.] q. d.</hi> If you do not Repent, you are undone, if you doe repent, but not throughly, you wil be undone too: hypocriſie in good duties, as well as profaneneſſe in bad wayes may ruine a perſon and Nation; A man may as ſurely be drowned in a ſhip that hath a leake, as when he hath no ſhip at all.</p>
            <p>Therefore pretend Repentance no longer, but act it, and when you doe act it, act it not ſlightly but exactly; become good, and do good to purpoſe: If you regard and follow this Counſell, Then (as in ver. 1.) you ſhall not remove; but if you will not hearken unto it, then (as in ver. 4.) <hi>My fury ſhall come
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:156756:6"/>
forth like fire,</hi> and burne that none can quench it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the evill of your doings.</p>
            <p>The words of my Text containe in them the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall works of this day, which are two,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A ſerious humiliation, unto which the <hi>Iewes</hi> are exhorted in theſe words <hi>[Break up your Fallow ground]</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. A dextrous Reformation, delivered unto them by way of caution <hi>[And ſow not among thornes:]</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>There muſt bee not a little raſing, but a breaking, nor a meere breaking, but a breaking up, and when that is done, there muſt bee a ſowing too, but every ſowing muſt not ſerve the turne, It muſt bee ſuch a ſowing, as may come to ſomething, It muſt not be a ſowing among thornes.</p>
            <p>The field which I am at this time to worke upon and goe over (you ſee) is very large, there is much more ground in it then I can conveniently breake up and ſow, I ſhall though (by that Gods aſſiſtance who only is the Maker and breaker of hearts) ſet upon the whole worke, and Hee (in tender mercy) ſo accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and water and proſper His truths this day, that all our Fallow grounds may bee broken up, and then ſo graciouſly ſowne in righteouſneſſe, that wee and all the land may ſhortly Reape in mercy!</p>
            <p>I begin with the firſt part <hi>[Breake up your Fallow ground.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That theſe words are to be underſtood, not lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally but metaphorically, I make no queſtion, that any who heares me, doth queſtion: Interpreters (though) do vary ſomething in their conjectures. <hi>Tertullian</hi> by fallow ground underſtands the old Law, which hee <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Adverſus Iudaeos. c.</hi> 3.</note> ſaith is to be broken up by the new Law (he meanes the Goſpel,) an expoſition much impertinent, and too wide.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:156756:6"/>
               <hi>Caſsianus</hi> underſtands by it, the Heathens and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, and other ſecular perſons, nor is this conject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure apt to the Text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cyprian</hi> drawes nearer to the ſenſe, who by fallow ground, underſtands <hi>(Mores popuſi)</hi> the converſations of the <hi>Iewes;</hi> and <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi> who by it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands, <hi>(Animum ſylveſcentem)</hi> an heart like the wilderneſſe, wilde and deſtitute of all pious culture, and <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> yet more exactly by fallow ground underſtands <hi>(cordis profundum)</hi> the very Core and depths of a ſinfull heart.</p>
            <p>So then (to ſtop all quotations) the fallow ground <note place="margin">The Fallow ground is the ſinfull heart.</note> is nothing elſe but the ſinfull eſtate of a perſon or Nation; And it is very aptly ſo deſcribed by reaſon of that conſimilitude which the one hath with the other, For;</p>
            <p>Firſt, Fallow ground is a barren piece of earth: a <hi>Tohu</hi> and <hi>Bohu</hi> as at the firſt, voyd of all excellency and beauty: There is not one graine of good ſeed <note place="margin">So reſemb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in three re</note> in it, nor any one delightfull flower; ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart is mans ſinfull heart: It is a very <hi>(Inane &amp; Nihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum)</hi> vanity and vanity, no divine excellency is to be found there; Not any one effect, nor any one ſeed of ſpirituall inclination: For this, It may anſwer as the depth did for wiſedome, <hi>It is not in me.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob 28. 14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Fallow ground is (uſually) an indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted Thicket, lumbred all over with weedes, and Briars, and Thornes, and Thiſtles, (that originall curſe which befell the Earth for mans tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:) And ſuch a piece alſo is mans ſinfull heart Though it bee but a barren Wilderneſſe for any good, yet it is an ample Ocean for all that is evill, and hurtfull. The upper part of his field hath in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:156756:7"/>
it an abundance of thornes (unprofitable thoughts, hurtfull cares, wounding errors;) and the lower part of his field is as full of ſtinking weedes (vile affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as the Apoſtle calls them:) the beſt fruits of him are but as a briar to ſcratch himſelfe, and to catch and intangle others with ſin.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Fallow ground is an hardned part of earth, extreamly compacted by the influences of the ſun and windes, and by its owne native inclination; ſo that it is not an eaſie thing to ſever it, and diſpoſe it for a better uſe: juſt ſo is a naturall, or ſinfull heart; It is ſo troden, and ſeared &amp; obdurated, partly by the frequent repetition of ſinful acts, and partly by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion of ſinfull delights, that it is not only defective of good, but alſo very active againſt it, unyeelding, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting, and fighting againſt all heavenly counſels and motions. The man is evill, and will be ſo, he is not good, nor will he be ſo, unleſſe <hi>God</hi> by an inſuperable vertue of his own ſpirit makes him to be ſo.</p>
            <p>We have found what the fallow ground is, let us in the next place inquire, what the breaking of it up <note place="margin">The break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up: what?</note> is? Then the Fallow ground is broken up, when the Husbandman comes with his Plow, and enters that plow into it, deepely enters it, even into the Bowels of the ground, and then rents and teares it, and turns it upſide downe: Not in one Furrow, but in every Furrow, once, twice, perhaps thrice if need ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires.</p>
            <p>Even ſo the ſinfull heart is broken up when the Almighty and gracious God (whom Chriſt calls <hi>the Husbandman)</hi> comes with his Word and Spirit, and <hi>(Alta voce</hi> as St. <hi>Austine</hi> ſpeaks, or <hi>virtute magnifica</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn 15. 1.</note> as <hi>Ber.</hi> ſpeaks) enters into the heart or ſoule of a ſinner
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:156756:7"/>
by irreſiſtable convincings, and by efficacious humb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings (w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> are as rentings and tearings to the ground) and by rooting up the dominion and love of all ſins.</p>
            <p>The Scriptures ſometimes call this worke, a touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſometimes a pricking, ſometimes a troubling, <note place="margin">Acts 2. 37. 1 Sam. 1. 5. Pſal. 34. 18. Prov. 18. 14. Iſa. 42. 3. Ioel 2. 13. 2 King. 22. 19.</note> ſometimes a wounding, ſometimes a bruiſing, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a breaking, ſometimes a renting, ſometimes a killing, and ſometimes an humbling and melting of the heart.</p>
            <p>And this is it which God calls for in the Text from the <hi>Iewes</hi> as a meanes to prevent their utter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction by the ſword of the <hi>Caldeans;</hi> whence the propoſition (which I ſhall in the firſt place inſiſt on) is this,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>1</label>
               <hi>That the breaking up of ſinfull hearts, Is a ſingular meanes to prevent the breaking downe of a ſinfull Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THere are three things unto which I ſhall ſpeake for the explication of this aſſertion, Namely</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. What the right breaking of a ſinfull heart is, which is ſo availeable to prevent the breaking downe of a ſinfull Nation?</item>
               <item>2. Some demonſtrations that it is a preventing meanes.</item>
               <item>3. The Reaſons why it is ſo?</item>
            </list>
            <p>For the firſt quaere, what the right breaking up of <note place="margin">a <hi>Queſt.</hi> 1.</note> a ſinfull heart is? Be pleaſed to know that there is a twofold Breaking of a ſinners heart. <note place="margin">Sol.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. One is ſpecious only and formall <hi>(ſuperſicie te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The heart broken for ſin 2 Wayes 1. Formally.</note> as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeakes) as Artificiall Juglars ſeem to wound themſelves, but do not; or as Players
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:156756:8"/>
ſeeme to thruſt themſelves through their bodies, but the ſword paſſeth only through their clothes: There is ſomething done about ſins, but nothing is done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſins; <hi>peccata raduntur ſed non eradicantur,</hi> as the ſame Auhor ſpeaketh, which he truely calls a Ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and vanity; As when men onely lop the Trees, which thereupon in time grow the faſter and thicker. Againſt this breaking the Prophet of old much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained; They in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> hung downe their heads and afflicted their ſoules for a day, but for all that they <note place="margin">Eſa. 58. 5, &amp; 3</note> ſtill afflicted their poore brethren; And they in <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſea,</hi> did howle, but yet they did ſtill rebell againſt the <note place="margin">Hoſea 7. 14.</note> Lord; And they in <hi>Malachy</hi> did cry out, and cover <note place="margin">Malach. 2. 13. &amp; 11.</note> the Altar with Teares, and yet for all their preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded contrition, they did profane the holineſſe of their God: And though the Phariſees did aſſume unto themſelves a moſt mortified garbe of humbling (eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in their dayes of Faſting disfiguring their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as Chriſt reports of them) yet their hearts were as looſe, as full of pride, and covetouſneſſe, and envie, <note place="margin">Matth. 6. 16.</note> and oppoſition of Chriſt, as ever.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another is ſerious and Reall; which is acted moſt in the hidden man, and pierceth like the word, <hi>(Hebr.</hi> 4. 12.) even to the dividing of ſoule and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, of which likewiſe there are two kindes, one is ſtiled Attrition, and the other is ſtyled Contrition by the Schoolemen; the former (by our Caſuiſts) is called a legall breaking, and the latter an Evangelicall breaking.
<q>
                  <l>They difference them thus, partly,</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. By their objects. Penall evill is the object on which Attrition doth worke, and ſinfull evill is the object on which Contrition worketh; the one is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:156756:8"/>
converſant about paſſive evill (that is) the evill which wee ſuffer, but the other is converſant about Active evill (that is) the evill which wee have done; For ſinne hath in it two qualities, one, to make us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie, and this Attrition lookes at; another to make us unholy, and at this doth contrition look.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By their cauſes, legall Attrition is onely the pinching of ſervile feare and deſpaire, for it ſeeth nothing but Sea, all that will teare and diſtract the Conſcience; but Evangelicall contrition is the mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and lamenting of filiall Love, and Hope: The frownes of a Revenging Judge cauſeth that; but the ſmiles of a gracious Father raiſeth this; In the one the heart is ſhivered by the flaſhes of Hell, In the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the heart is melted by the beames of Heaven; A ſtroke from guilt brake Judas's heart into deſpaire, but a looke from CHRIST brake <hi>Peters</hi> heart in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to teares.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By their effects, an Attrite heart may (for that ſpace of time whiles the Conſcience burnes and flames with wrath) become negatively penitent, <hi>Non proponit peccare,</hi> It doth not purpoſe to ſin; the ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble anguiſh for former ſinnings may ſuſpend delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full intentions for future ſins; but the contrite heart (out of a contrariety of nature) becomes poſitively holy, <hi>proponit non peccare,</hi> It doth Cordially purpoſe not to ſin any more; All which (if I miſtake not) is the ſame that <hi>Cajetan</hi> aimes at, when hee ſaith, that Attrition produceth <hi>(velleitatem)</hi> an imperfect mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the will, but contrition produceth <hi>(volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem)</hi> a compleat and direct will againſt ſin:</p>
            <p>But this diſcourſe (I feare) is too ſpeculative for this dayes worke, give mee leave therefore to open
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:156756:9"/>
the nature of this penitentiall heart breaking in a more practicall and profitable way: There are ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall workings which ordinarily concurre to the full conſtituting of this heart-breaking worke, whereof ſome are Antecedent, ſome are formally ingredient, and ſome are inſeparably conſequent.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Antecedent workings are ſuch as previ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly lead the way to the Evangelicall breaking as <note place="margin">Antecedents to heart breaking three.</note> the Needle doth to the threed, and the breaking by the hammer doth to the melting by the fire, by way of order only and not by cauſality: Theſe are (prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally) three.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A Notionall Irradiation: The Lord never breakes a ſinners heart before hee hath opened a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners <note place="margin">1. Irradiation</note> eyes: the day breakes before the heart breakes: light breakes to elevate the ſoule, thus far to diſcerne and diſtinguiſh of evill; till then, ſin is no burden to the Conſcience, nor trouble to the affections: As no good wrapt up in darkeneſſe excites deſire, ſo no evill ſwath'd up in Ignorance ſtrikes any trouble or ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row: unknowne things, have not motive faculty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are as <hi>(non entia)</hi> no things at all: And therefore God ever keepes this method, to make ſin appeare to be ſin, and afterwards to humble and break our hearts for it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A practicall conviction, which is nothing elſe but a perſonall application of guilt &amp; wrath, without <note place="margin">2. Conviction</note> which the notion of ſin would be no trouble: let me open my minde thus unto you: That drunkenneſſe, or ſwearing, or whoredome, or murder, or Sabbath breaking, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are ſins; And that ſuch perſons who are guilty of them, (without Repentance) <hi>ſhall not inherit the kingdome of God,</hi> All this the ſinner knowes
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:156756:9"/>
already<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and yet is not troubled, for as long as light reſts in a bare Notion, it is only an addition to his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, It is no burden at all to his heart: But when this light ſlips downe, and chargeth this ſinne and this wrath upon this very perſon, and ſhines ſo clearely in this charge, that the perſon cannot for his life deny it, thou art a drunkard, thou art this ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And hereupon in the name of God arreſts him with that wrath which God hath threatned unto that ſinne and ſinner, now the ſinner begins to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and tremble, and breake.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Peter</hi> cloſed with the Jewes, and convinced <note place="margin">Acts 2. 36, 37.</note> them that they (in particular<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>crucified Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> Now their h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ts were pricked: and when <hi>Nathan</hi> drawes his parable out of the cloud, and unclothes his Meſſage to <hi>David,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Thou art the man,</hi> Now <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12. 7. Pſalme 51.</note> 
               <hi>Davids</hi>'s heart begins to breake and take on; O ſee! the ſubtile heart of man will endure and beare all the Hiſtorical Notions of ſin (as we can the names and natures of diſeaſes and medicines) without any aking and ſickneſſe; But when the Lord brings downe ſin from being a notion, to be an obligation, and enters an action againſt the ſoule within the ſoule, now (and not before) the heart-workings, and heart-breakings doe begin.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A Conſcience affliction: which in reſpect of <note place="margin">3. Affliction.</note> degrees and quantity, is, in ſome more, and in others leſſe: for Gods Spirit is an Arbitrary agent in the Graduall effects of bondage as well as in thoſe gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious effects of Adoption; Nevertheleſſe though the degrees of working be different, yet the worke it ſelfe is certaine; The heart will never bee rightly broken for ſin, till Conſcience (which Saint <hi>Bernard</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:156756:10"/>
calls Accuſer, Witneſſe, Judge, and Tormentor) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to be awakened and quickned: And believe it if <note place="margin">The terrible workings of conſcience.</note> Conſcience which hath been ſo much ſtirred begins to ſtirre, if Conſcience which hath beene ſo often wounded begins to wound, the ſpirit of man will eftſoone faile and breake within him; O ſaith Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience! What haſt thou done, thus and thus to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the Holy and Righteous and Great God. I know the ſeverall acts of thy ſinnings, and times, and places, and perſons, and circumſtances; and I have ſad newes to tell thee, that great God (againſt whom thou haſt ſo much and ſo often ſinned) hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and deputed me not only to ſpeake no peace, but alſo to ſpeake His wrath and diſpleaſure unto thee, and in His Name I charge upon thee all thy ſins and all his juſt wrath revealed againſt them.</p>
            <p>And now the proud and ſtout heart of a ſinner begins to throb and feare and tremble: He thinkes that every threatning which he reades, is a Cloud of Tempeſts againſt him, hee thinkes that every judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hee heares of another, is a Sword drawne to cut him off alſo; He thinkes that all the hell and torments thereof mentioned in the Scriptures, will ere long bee his portion; whereupon his diſtracted ſoule cries out, ô that I had never beene! ô that I had never ſinned! ô that I might never bee! If I ſhould now dye, good Lord! what will become of mee? If I ſhould yet live, will the Lord ever bee mercifull to me? The ſins which I ſee are many, the wrath which I feele is great, and that which I feare is infinite: If I live, I ſee I am an accurſed creature, and if I dye (ô let me not yet dye!) I feare I ſhall bee for ever (ô my ſoule breakes at that endleſſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:156756:10"/>
word of miſery, for ever!) a damned ſinner: But yet cries out this ſinner, Lord! Lord! Is there no mercy, nor hope of any mercy for mee, a moſt vile ſinner?</p>
            <p>With theſe minde racking-breaking thoughts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way haſtens this burdened, broken ſinner unto his Cloſet, and ſhuts the doore, and downe hee fals on his knees, and with much confuſion of thoughts and feares hee ſpreads all his ſinnings before God, confeſſing one, and then another, and then with fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent agonies begges of the Lord (more than for his life) Mercy Lord! mercy, mercy for a loſt, for an heinous, for an undone ſinner! Canſt thou pardon me? Wilt thou pardon me? O Lord pardon mee! O Lord bee reconciled unto mee! O that I might have any hopes, the leaſt hopes, that thou wouldeſt be mercifull unto me!</p>
            <p>And now up riſeth this ſinner with theſe or the like thoughts, well! I will reade the Bible, I will heare ſuch a Miniſter, I will open my condition unto him, and conferre, and inquire whither there bee no balme in <hi>Gilead:</hi> whither there be a mercy Seate, a Citie of refuge to entertaine ſuch a ſinner as I am; and after a while upon carefull ſearch, he findes that yet there is hope, that there is an immeaſurable ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciencie in the bloud of Chriſt, &amp; an Ocean of ful and free grace in God, and that God (notwithſtanding all his former ſinnings againſt him) is moſt willing and ready to accept of him into mercy, if ſo bee, hee bee willing to forſake his ſinnes and imbrace a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:156756:11"/>
               <head>2. The formall Ingredients.</head>
               <p>HEreupon followes the ſecond principall work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Ingredients of heart breaking two Ier. 31, 19.</note> which formally makes up Evangelicall Contrition, and it is (1. <hi>Pudor.</hi> 2. <hi>Dolor,)</hi> ſhame and griefe: Such kindneſſe from the mercy-ſeate makes him now as <hi>Ephraim,</hi> confounded and aſhamed, and his heart to breake into moſt melting flouds of teares, that ever he ſhould bee ſo monſtrouſly vile to offend ſuch tender and gracious bowels of mercy, which hee now apprehends yerning towards him in and through Chriſt. As before, the apprehenſions of divine wrath did diſtract and ſhiver him, ſo now the apprehenſions of divine love doe totally diſſolve and melt him; though there were not Heaven hereafter to Crowne him, yet he muſt grieve, and though there were not Hell hereafter to burne him, yet he muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly mourn for ſinning againſt ſuch a God.</p>
               <p>This is that right Evangelicall Contrition which I preſſe for at this time! called in Scripture, a ſoftneſſe of heart, and a contrite Heart, and a mourning, and a bitter mourning, and a great mourning, like that of <hi>Hadadrimmon</hi> in the Valley of <hi>Megiddon:</hi> which <note place="margin">Zac. 12. 10, 11.</note> Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> calls <hi>(Cor liqueſcens)</hi> an heart melting, and diſſolving, and Saint <hi>Hierome (magnum planctum)</hi> an exceeding lamenting; and St. <hi>Auſtin (grave lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum)</hi> a very heavie griefe.</p>
               <p>The Caſuiſts and Schoolmen affirme it to bee the <note place="margin">Sorrow for ſin the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſorrow in 4. reſpects. <hi>Adrianus. Scotus. Soto.</hi>
                  </note> greateſt of all ſorrows. 1. <hi>In conatu,</hi> the whole ſoule ſeemes to ſend ſprings into it out of every faculty. 2. <hi>In extenſione,</hi> It is a ſpring which in this life (more or leſſe) is continually dropping. 3. <hi>In appreciatione,</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:156756:11"/>
the changed ſoule doth ever judge that a good God offended, ſhould be the prime cauſe of greateſt ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and Laſtly, <hi>In intenſione,</hi> For Intenſion of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicence in the will, there being no o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her things, with which, or for which the will is more diſpleaſed with it ſelfe then for ſinning againſt God. And therefore ſome of the Schoolemen propounding this queſtion <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sot in 4. Sent. d. 17. q. 2. art.</hi> 4.</note> whether there ſhould be more griefe for ſin, then for the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſion of Chriſt? Reſolve it Affirmatively, that there is more cauſe of griefe for ſinning, then for the death of Chriſt: and their reaſon is this, becauſe in the death of Chriſt there was <hi>(Aliquid placens)</hi> Something that did pleaſe God, ſo farre as it was a Redemption, but ſin is <hi>(ſimpliciter diſplicens)</hi> there is nothing in it which is not altogether diſpleaſing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, conſider it formally as ſin.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>3. The conſequent working.</head>
               <p>WHich rather ſhewes and declares, then makes a broken heart, and it is hatred of ſin; the <note place="margin">Hatred of ſin the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent of heart break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for ſin. A double ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of ſin.</note> heart which is rightly broken, is not only broken for ſin, but alſo from ſin by an hatred. 1. Of abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, loathing it as the greateſt evill: <hi>Get thee hence ſay they in, Eſa.</hi> 30. 22. And 2. Of enmi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reconciliation, <hi>what have I to doe any more with Idols,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ephraim</hi> in <hi>Hoſea</hi> 14. 8.</p>
               <p>Thus have you heard what the <hi>breaking up of the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ground,</hi> or ſinfull heart is, now I proceed (in few words) to demonſtrate, That it is the meanes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the breaking downe of a ſinfull Nation; this <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 2.</note> may evidently appeare.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:156756:12"/>1. By the fingers of God in Scripture pointing a <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sol.</hi> 4. Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of the propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in its truth.</note> people to this worke, that ſo they might not ſinke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ruine, but be preſerved: Read <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 18. 30, 31. <hi>Ioel</hi> 2. 13, 14.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By the pledges which God maketh in ſeverall promiſes, that if a ſinfull Nation will take this courſe, he will then ſpare them, and continue them: Read, <hi>Ier.</hi> 18. 7, 8. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7. 14.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By the Records or Inſtances of Gods ſparing a people, and a revoking of his wrath and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments when they have ſet upon this Heart-breaking courſe, Read <hi>Ionah</hi> 3. 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. 2 <hi>Chronicles</hi> 34. 27.</p>
               <p n="4">4. By the executions of deſtruction becauſe they would not hearken to this courſe, See 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 36. 15, 16, 17.</p>
               <p>But why ſhould the breaking up of ſinfull hearts bee a meanes to prevent the breaking downe of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 3.</note> Nation? The Reaſons are theſe, becauſe</p>
               <p>Firſt, where hearts are rightly broken for ſinnes, there ſinnes are pardoned: and where ſinnes are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sol.</hi> 4. Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the propoſition. 2 Chro. 7. 14. Eſay. 1. 16.</note> all breaking down is unqueſtionably preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. In <hi>Eſaiah,</hi> you reade of <hi>waſhing and cleanſing</hi> (they are the ſame with this heart-breaking and mourning) and preſently you reade of pardon, <hi>Though your ſinnes be as ſcarlet, they ſhall bee as white as ſnow,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">18.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and preſently after that, you reade, <hi>of eating the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">19.</note> 
                  <hi>good of the Land:</hi> a comfortable fruition of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and of their Country, and of all meanes and bleſſings.</p>
               <p>Beloved! when ſinnes are pardoned then, <note place="margin">2. Effects of ſins pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. All their guilty clamour is ſilenced: pardoned ſins are diſabled ſins, they can bring no action againſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:156756:12"/>
us, debts forgiven ſhall never prejudice nor hurt us: Sins unpardoned can raiſe <hi>poſſe comitatus,</hi> all the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies <note place="margin">Remiſſa culpa remittitur paena.</note> of God in Heaven and Earth againſt ſinners, but once pardoned, they are of no force or ſtrength at all.</p>
               <p>And ſecondly, when ſins are pardoned, all good hath a free paſſage; God is reconciled, and mercies have their Commiſſion to attend us: Now ſaith the Lord, <hi>I will heare the Heavens, and they ſhall heare the earth, and the earth ſhall heare the Corne, and the Wine</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Hoſ. 2. 21, 22</note> 
                  <hi>and the Oyle, and they ſhall heare Iezreel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Againe, If ſinfull hearts be broken, God hath his end, and then all quarrels ceaſe twixt him and a <note place="margin">2.</note> Nation: the Lord doth not threaten deſtruction to a people for deſtructions ſake, but for Humiliations ſake: Not that they may be deſtroyed, but that they ſhould repent, and not be deſtroyed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, Broken hearts are a wonderfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light unto the Lord: There are ſomethings in which <note place="margin">3.</note> God hath no delight, He hath no delight <hi>in ſinnings,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm. 5. 4. Ezek. 18. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>nor in puniſhments:</hi> and there are two hearts in which God takes much delight, namely, <hi>in an upright heart and in a Contrite heart, The broken heart hee will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe,</hi> nay hee will looke upon that heart to revive it: If broken hearts be Gods delight, and the objects of <note place="margin">Pſal. 51. 17. Eſa. 57. 15.</note> his reviving, then without queſtion they are a means to prevent deſtruction.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Laſtly, when hearts are broken for ſins, then <hi>Gods</hi> heart (if I may ſo phraſe it) is broken with compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions unto ſinners: Though ſinners remaine obſtinate yet divine compaſſions work ſtrongly towards them, <hi>(How ſhall I give thee up,</hi> Ephraim? <hi>how ſhall I deliver thee, O</hi> Iſrael? <hi>&amp;c. Hoſea</hi> 11. 8.) what bowels then
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:156756:13"/>
(thinke you) are working in God when ſinners are broken and humbled and turning? If God can ſo hardly finde the way to puniſh impenitent <hi>Ephraim,</hi> will he not find the way to ſpare an humbling <hi>Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im,</hi> See <hi>Ier.</hi> 31. 18. <hi>I have ſurely heard</hi> Ephraim <hi>lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himſelfe,</hi> &amp;c. 20. <hi>My bowels are troubled for him, I will ſurely have mercy upon him ſaith the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have done with the explication of the point, I now addreſſe my ſelfe to the Application of it.</p>
               <p>1. To all of us. 2. To you of publike employment.</p>
               <p>Is the breaking up of ſinfull hearts, the means to prevent the breaking downe of a ſinning Nation? <note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> 
                  <hi>Then let every one of us</hi> here, (ô that the whole Land alſo would) <hi>ſearch and try the temper and frame of our hearts,</hi> whither they be broken or unbroken? Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved! I beſeech you ſadly to conſider of a few things.</p>
               <p>1. That brokenneſſe of heart is the worke of this <note place="margin">6. Things conſiderable, about bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe of heart.</note> day: This is a day of Humiliation; but what is an humbling day without an humbled heart? to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent your ſelves before the great God, at ſuch a time, with all your ſinnes, and yet without hearts broken for thoſe ſins, is not only an irreligious incongruity, but alſo an high provocation of our God; like <hi>Zim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> act when all the <hi>Congregation were weeping before the doore of the Tabernacle, Numb.</hi> 25. 6.</p>
               <p>Come we not this day with all ſorts of guilt upon our ſoules, and with ropes about our neckes, expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (if the Lord ſhould render unto us our deſerts) the ſentence of death, and confeſſe as much, and yet dare we to play the Hypocrites, having hearts under all this utterly unbroken?</p>
               <p>Secondly, brokenneſſe of heart, is the hope of this
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:156756:13"/>
day: I profeſſe ſeriouſly unto you, that were you as much in faſting as <hi>Iohns</hi> Diſciples, and in praying as Chriſts Diſciples, could you by Faſting make your knees to faint, and your fleſh to faile, and reſolve your bodies into a very Sceleton, if yet your hearts were not broken for your ſins, Neither your ſelves, nor your endaevours, nor our owne Nation, nor the diſtreſſed Church of <hi>Ireland,</hi> nor any other would bee the better for it: As one of the Fathers ſaid of Learning, All learning is ſuſpected, nay diſreſpected by me, wherein is not the mention of Chriſt, that I affirme of all ſolemne faſtings whatſoever, the Lord regards them not, if the broken heart bee not found in them.</p>
               <p>What <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſaid to his brethren, unleſſe you bring your brother <hi>Benjamin</hi> with you, you ſhall not ſee my face, or as <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſaid to his Father, <hi>Behold the Fire and the Wood, but where is the Lambe for a burnt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering?</hi> That the Lord ſaith unto us, <hi>Faſt as often as you pleaſe, and pray too, unleſſe your hearts bee broken for your ſinnes, nothing that you doe ſhall finde favour with me; all the reſt is but as wood and fire, the Lambe, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of a Contrite heart</hi> (which is that I look at, and for,) <hi>is wanting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Get thee behinde me ſaid</hi> Jehu <hi>to the ſeverall meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, what have you to doe with peace? Confeſsions, and prayers are the meſſengers of our ſoules to God,</hi> but unleſſe the ſinful heart be broken, they will never be meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of peace.</p>
               <p>If any of you would angle in a River, would you throw in a naked line only? would this be to any pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe? Sirs! I know well, that if a Faſt bee rightly performed, it hath as many promiſes of bleſſings and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:156756:14"/>
mercies (See <hi>Eſay</hi> 58.) As any religious duty what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever: Nay, and I thinke that you never read in all the Bible, nor yet in experience, of its right perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance without ſome ſudden and remarkeable Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Gods gracious acceptance and anſwer: But then breaking of hearts ever accompanied thoſe prevailing and victorious Faſts, as you may Reade in <hi>Iudges,</hi> and <hi>Samuel,</hi> and the <hi>Kings,</hi> and <hi>Ezra,</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> &amp;c. And for my part, I ſhould not ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the aſſecution of any convenient mercy, nor the diverſion of any impendent evill, if once with all our Faſtings, there were alſo a breaking up of our Fallow grounds: If GOD could in this command our hearts, we might then (in ſome ſenſe) command our God:</p>
               <p>3. Thirdly, Have wee not all of us ſufficient cauſe to breake our ſinfull hearts? Should ſinnes, ſhould calamities abroad, ſhould dangers at home breake hearts? all theſe may then worke upon us: our ſins have broken the heart of CHRIST, and are ſuch as have broken off God from a people, and have broken many Churches downe: Can you bee igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the profeſſed Idolatry in this Land? of the horrid blaſphemies? of the over-flowing drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? of the Sabbaths profanation? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if wee looke at calamities abroad, why, as <hi>Iacob</hi> ſaid, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> is not, and <hi>Simeon</hi> is not, ſo may we ſay, <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia</hi> is broken up, and the <hi>Palatinate</hi> is broken up, and <hi>IRELAND</hi> is breaking up, and yet the hearts of ſinfull <hi>England</hi> will not bee broken up: Nay if wee looke at the dangers hovering like a Cloud over this Land, and dropping already in manifold and ſundry diviſions, in manifold plots, in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:156756:14"/>
manifold and ſeverall contradictions, and even rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to breake forth (O LORD let it not breake forth) in a bitter inteſtine Warre amongſt our ſelves, where every mans ſword ſhall bee againſt his brother, and the Child may kill the Parent, or the Parent kill his Child (bowels ſheathed in bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els,) No man ſcarce ſecure in his owne Family, our ſins are bringing this upon us, and yet our hearts will not breake for theſe ſinnes! The God of all Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and mercies breake our hearts, that ſo this judgement may not doe that which all our forreigne enemies hitherto could not doe, Breake downe our Church and Nation.</p>
               <p>4. And if judgements ſhould breake in upon ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, before hearts are broken for ſins, good Lord! what, where are they? <hi>Dudilius</hi> relates a ſad ſtory of <hi>Bochna</hi> a woman who had but two ſonnes, and whiles ſhe was walking with the one towards the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, ſhe heard the other crying out, and haſtning back, ſhee found a knife ſticking in him, which kild him quickly, then ſhe returnes to her other child thinking to ſolace her ſelfe in an onely child, but he in her ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence was fallen into the river and drowned, both loſt at once: Ah Sirs! we have but two children, a Soule and a body! what an heavie loſſe will it bee to loſe both theſe at once? To bee cut off by an angry ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie and to be caſt off by a mighty God! To loſe a life, and at the ſame time to lofe an eternall life! To loſe ſafety and ſalvation at once? Tis true that if a ſinners heart be broken by grace, there is no queſtion of mercy, but when an impenitent ſinners life is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by judgment, his hopes are gone, and his break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it for ever.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:156756:15"/>5. Fifthly, Wee ſhall aſſuredly be broken off, if we be not broken up; Beloved! There are two vile malignities in an unbroken heart.</p>
               <p>Firſt, It is one of the greateſt of ſpirituall judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ô ſaid a Reverend man once, if I muſt be put to my option, I had rather be in Hell with a ſenſible heart, then live on earth with a reprobate minde; ſo I ſay, an hardned and unbroken heart (is in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect) a judgement worſe than Hell, for as much as one of the greateſt ſins, is farre greater in evill, then any of the greateſt puniſhments.</p>
               <p>Secondly, It is the immediate and unavoydable forerunner of the greateſt of temporall judgements, <hi>He that hardens his heart ſhall be deſtroyed ſuddenly and that without remedy, Prov.</hi> 29. 1. Obſerve that place: There is no leſſe then deſtruction, which is not a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular and imperfect dammage, but it is a compleate ruine, and this deſtruction is certaine (ſhall, not may perhaps, bee deſtroyed) but when? Suddenly! I! but the ſinner wil ſhift it off, &amp; withſtand it! No, but hee ſhall bee deſtroyed without remedy: His deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſhall not be prevented; you may reade all this in the old World, and in <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and in the <hi>Iewes</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Babylonian Captivitie, and afterwards in the Roman divaſtation which hath laſted theſe 1600 yeares.</p>
               <p>6. But now where are our broken hearts? I know not what to ſay, my heartakes within mee, ô that it could bee broken becauſe hearts are generally unbro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: Sinners are ſecure, Conſciences are ſeared, wickedneſſe is bold, ſinnes are a delight and paſtime, God is not ſeene nor feared in his judgements, in His warnings, in His dealings; Reformation is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:156756:15"/>
Humiliation (moſt know not what it meanes, and if they doe) it is diſtaſted: Serious thoughts of our ſinfull wayes who takes them up? ſufficient time for ſelfe-examination who makes it for himſelfe? every man runnes on in his courſe, loves as hee did, lives as he did; And never knew a trouble in his ſoule, nor a teare in his eye either for his owne, or for the ſins of others, all his dayes: And what will the end of all this be?</p>
               <p>O that God would pittie us this day, and breake our hearts for us! though it bee ſo irkſome and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to our fleſh and bloud: It is better (ſaid a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) to dye one death, then to live and feare all deaths: better it is to ſuffer the heart to bee broken, then to expoſe our ſelves to all ſorts of Judiciall &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall breakings: ô Lord ſaid dying <hi>Fulgen. (Dapae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentiam &amp; poſtea indulgentiam)</hi> make mee a penitent ſinner, and then let me find thee an indulgent Father: Never looke for great mercies, for long mercies, for any mercies with unbroken hearts; we are not good, we can doe no good, we can expect no good, till our ſinfull hearts be broken: O Chriſtians be perſwaded this day to get broken hearts! God can do it for you, and will doe it for you, if you will but uſe the means and ſeeke unto him: ſpare time, and take it to ſtudy the Law, to ſtudy Conſcience, to ſtudy the Goſpell, to ſtudy mercies, to ſtudy judgements, to ſtudy Chriſt, to ſtudy all, that after all, our hearts may bee broken for our ſinnes, that ſo God may not breake away from us, but continue to be our God, and that judgements (which looke ſo blacke upon us may be broken off, and plots (contriv'd againſt us) may breake aſunder, and all ſpirituall and earthly mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:156756:16"/>
may breake downe in mercy upon us.</p>
               <p>And thus much bee ſpoken with a reſpect unto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that heareth mee this day, I have beſides all this a particular errand from God to you, who are publike perſons, and have ſummond me this day unto <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vſe</hi> 2.</note> this publike worke, me thinkes that the Lord ſpeakes to you in ſome reſpect what once he ſpake to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> Chap. 1. Verſe 10. See, <hi>I have this day ſet you over the Nations, and over the Kingdomes to roote out, and to pull downe, and to destroy, and to throw downe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And bleſſed bee the Lord, and bleſſed bee your ſoules, and bleſſed be your endeavours, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the infinite difficulty of the worke, and the Malignant contrariety you meet with, yet your hearts are undaunted and reſolved to finiſh the work, as Honourable, as ever Parliament undertooke, and as profitable to Church and State, as ever Chriſtians enterpriſed, your armes ſhall bee made ſtrong by the bleſſing of the everlaſting God of <hi>Iacob,</hi> let popiſh and malevolent and ignorant perſons ſay or doe what they can: Give me leave. 1. To repreſent unto you <note place="margin">The work of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> ſome publike plots of fallow-ground, which you (bleſſed be God) have begun to breake, nevertheleſſe they need yet a more full breaking up.</p>
               <p>Secondly, to preſent in all humble fidelity unto you ſome few intimations and directions.
<q>
                     <l>1. The publike plots of Fallow ground which need a further breaking up, are (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially) foure. <note place="margin">4. Grounds to be broken up.</note>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt lies directly in the valley of <hi>Hinnom:</hi> and it is Idolatry; a piece of ground which lies too much in every Shire of this Land, what County is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:156756:16"/>
there where much Popery is not? Sirs! you muſt breake this ground up, or it will breake our Land up: There is not ſuch a God-povoking ſinne, a God-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving ſin, a Church-diſſolving ſinne, a kingdome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breaking ſin as Idolatry, the ſoule of God abhorres it: down with it, down with it even to the ground.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond lies neare to <hi>Beth-Aven,</hi> and it is ſuperſtition: which is but a bawd to groſſe Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try: As rife in practiſe (even now) notwithſtanding all that you have ſaid and done, as if a Parliament had never opened a mouth againſt it: If a due and carefull inquiry bee made, I queſtion not but you ſhall find in too many Churches and publike places, as many Altars, and as many Crucifixes hanging o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them, and as many Tapers on the Altars, and as much bowing towards the Eaſt, and Altar, almoſt as many, and as much, as when you began this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third lies juſt upon the coaſts of <hi>Egypt,</hi> that Land of darkneſſe; And it is ignorance, a very large circuit of ground this is; many, many places of this land there are which lie Fallow to this day, never any husbandman, nor Plow have entred in to breake up thoſe grounds: A moſt lamentable thing, that ſince <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> came into the world and ſince the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell is come into this Land, after ſeverall ſcores of yeares, yet how many Pariſhes in <hi>Wales,</hi> and in the <hi>North,</hi> and in other Counties which ſcarſely have enjoyed this much mercy as to heare one ſolid ſoule working Sermon concerning Chriſt and ſalvation by him; O Sirs! let your hearts bleed in pitty to theſe poore ſoules; liberties (I confeſſe) are preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſo are our eſtates, and ſo are bodies and lives,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:156756:17"/>
ô then what are ſoules? what are precious ſoules which did coſt the moſt precious bloud of the <hi>Lord Ieſus Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fourth ill plot of ground lies on <hi>Mizpah,</hi> or if you pleaſe on Mount <hi>Taber, for there the Prieſts</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">4.</note> 
                  <hi>were a Net, and a Snare, Hoſea</hi> 5. 1. And this is an idle and an evill miniſtry: Sirs! miſtake me not, I ſpeake not of our Miniſters indefinitely, I know that wee have as godly, as learned, as painefull, as profitable Miniſters as any in all the Chriſtian world, but I ſpeake onely of ſuch whoſe ſpeciall gifts conſiſt in one of theſe two things, either quietly to read out of a booke and diſcreetly to gather up their Tythes; or malevolently to diſcountenance all godlineſſe, and raile againſt the Parliament.</p>
               <p>Ah worthy Sirs! It would amaze any ingenuous man to travaile ſuch a Country as England and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing through many Pariſhes, this (after all) is his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urnall, the Patron is Popiſh, the Miniſter is an Idle Dunce, or elſe a drunkard, or elſe a ſwearer, or elſe a ſcoffer, preaching all holineſſe out of his pulpit out of his Church, out of his family, out of his Pariſh, and his people are like unto him, and love to have it ſo: And thus what betweene the Idle Miniſter and the evill Miniſter, the poore people never come to knowledge, or (without which knowledge never comes to any thing) they never come to the love and practiſe of any ſaving good: Theſe are the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall fallow grounds in this Land, which need your care and paines.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:156756:17"/>
               <head>2. Now follow the Intimations and directions which I humbly preſent unto you.</head>
               <p n="1">1. B Breake them up: If ever you will quit your owne ſoules, and the truſt repoſed in you, and <note place="margin">4. Directions about the breaking up of ill grounds</note> the whole land of Judgments ſpiritual and corporall, If ever you deſire to gaine ground in your publike intentions for good, for the Lords ſake breake up theſe Fallow grounds.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But then in the next place, goe very deepe with your Plow, or elſe you will never breake up theſe grounds: the deeper the better; As all good is moſt ſtrengthened, ſo all evill is moſt cruſhed in its cauſes: Take heed of ſhadow-worke, and ſurface-plowing: Gods eyes are upon you, and ſo are the eyes of judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious men, which can diſtinguiſh twixt ſcraping and breaking, our miſery will be but finely laid aſleepe a while if your plow goes not deepe.</p>
               <p>Doth a little cringing move you? ô then, let groſſe Idolatry heate and burne your ſoules! Doth bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in a queſtioned Miniſter diſpleaſe you? ô then let his groſſe wickedneſſe ſtirre you utterly to disbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den poore peoples ſoules of him: ô let ſad com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints have quicke and full redreſſes!</p>
               <p n="3">3. And goe over the Fallow grounds which you have broken, goe them over againe; Yea, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: Fallow grounds muſt be often broken up with the Plow. Even the actions of the moſt judicious receave more ripeneſſe by review: by often doing wee grow into a better acquaintance with what is to be done: our firſt doings are rather trialls and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes, the ſecond doings ever prove the beſt worke:
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:156756:18"/>
beſides that, our affections alſo are oftimes too quicke for our eyes, the deſires of doing ſome good may outrunne the due ſearch of much evill: Adde yet further, That ingrained diſeaſes are not eaſily ſtirred, much leſſe deſtroyed by one potion; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills long in gathering, and much baked into and ſetled in a State or Church, are not ſo ſuddenly cured as vulgar people in their haſte imagine: ſhall I ſpeake one thing more; There is as much Art al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as ſinne, as much guilt, as Guiltineſſe: The Lawes are ingenuous, but offendors are fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and ſubtile: Sirs! you deale with bold offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and with cunning offenders too, which (if you looke not the better to it) will quite delude and fruſtrate all your Religious and pious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions.</p>
               <p>Shall I tell you what I know, and what the Countrey ſighes and ſheds Teares at, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding your Religious pittie to their ſoules, yet their ſoules are as much abuſed as ever: They have complained of ſome ill Miniſters, you hearken unto them; but in the meane time, the Miniſter exchang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his living with another (perhaps) a far of, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to the people, againſt whom there can bee (for the preſent) No legall exception, and thus they periſh ſtill for want of bread:</p>
               <p>Therefore Worthy Sirs! Out with your plow againe, you are by all theſe after-workes much more directed how to mannage and carry on your worke.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Laſtly, Bee as earneſt and active as poſſibly you can to ſend Labourers into the Field, I meane, <note place="margin">4.</note> to plant all the Land with an heart-breaking mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery:
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:156756:18"/>
All will come to nothing unleſſe this bee done: Pluralities are Voted downe, but what good will that bee, when all comes but to this, before that Order, one bad man had two good livings, and now two bad men have each of them one too good for them both: I will ſay no more unto you; but be ſerious and couragious in this worke in ſetling of a good Miniſtery, with which joyne alſo an anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Magiſtracie: This to doe, is your duty, this is your honour, this will bee our ſafety and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, This will bee Your great reward in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
               <p>Goe on thus in this breaking-worke, and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: There is no man ever did any thing for God and loſt by it, or to his Church, but gained by it: If you will goe on with an humble and unwearied zeale, it ſhall ſhortly be ſaid of this Parliament, <hi>Theſe were Scotlands Vmpire, Irelands guard and revenge, Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands preſervation, The Churches ſafety, and religions glory:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo I paſſe from the Plow to the ſeed, from the plowing up of Fallow-grounds, to the ſowing of them being broken up, expreſſed with its caution in the Text.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>And ſow not among thornes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:156756:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Second Part.</hi> And ſow not among Thornes:</head>
               <p>THat a breaking up of the ground muſt goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a ſowing, and then that a ſowing muſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the breaking up, is no queſtion with any judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man; For as it were a vaine thing to ſow when the ground is not broken up (the ſeed would but be a prey) ſo it were as fooliſh when the ground is broken up, not to ſow (the labour would never prove an har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt) breaking up of the ground being in it ſelfe only <hi>(opus imperfectum &amp; reſpectivum)</hi> a worke for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">Sowing muſt follow breaking up.</note> worke; And indeed as the <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> ſpake of the Emperor that he rather wanted vice then was vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſo it may be ſaid of a perſon and Nation if their Fallow grounds be broken up, and yet be not ſowen, they are rather not wicked, then good, For Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives (alone) make no eſtate to be gracious; It muſt be ſome poſitive quality which gives perfection and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination; They ſay well in Philoſophy, that whiles the motion is paſſing from the <hi>Terminus a quo</hi> It is but in <hi>Fieri,</hi> and till the <hi>terminus ad quem</hi> bee at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, it is not in <hi>facto eſſe,</hi> the worke is but on the way, it is not at the end, nor done: The ſame is a truth in Divinity, for ceſſation from evill is not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient <note place="margin">Eſay 1. 16, 17.</note> without an operation of good; to pull downe wickedneſſe is not enough unleſſe we alſo ſet up god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe; <hi>Ioſiah</hi> did pull downe Idols, but then he did likewiſe reſtore and ſet up the true worſhip of God:
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:156756:19"/>
And our Saviour did not onely correct the falſe gloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes wherewith the Phariſees had corrupted the law, <note place="margin">Matth. 5. 21, 22, 28, 32, &amp;c.</note> but alſo erected and eſtabliſhed the true ſenſe and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine Interpretation of it: <hi>Iehu</hi> to this day lies under the tongue and cenſure of Hypocriſie, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all his zeale againſt <hi>Baal</hi> and the Prieſts, becauſe after all this, <hi>He tooke no care or heed to walke in the Law</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Kings 10. 27, 28, 31.</note> 
                  <hi>of the Lord God of Iſrael with all his heart,</hi> It is (I think) a true maxime, that all true quarrell with evill, ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth from the love of good: and therefore the defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cings and diſplacings of the former ought to end in the advancings and ſetlings of the latter; and verily it were a weake deſigne to undoe the one, and yet not to doe the other: becauſe,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Morall evills will not be cured, but by contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry qualities: A ſtate (like water though for a time heated, yet will ſlip backe to coldneſſe) will warp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout (after a while) to its corruptions, if care be not taken for its perfecting and preſervation too:</p>
               <p n="2">2. Againe, though a Nation bee ſomewhat leſſe miſerable, becauſe evill is removed, yet it will not bee happy till good bee planted; you ſhall finde, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this, that the ſoule of the publike ſtate will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer that of the perſon: To whom as the preſence of <hi>(Nocivum)</hi> what oppreſſeth him is a burden, ſo the abſence of <hi>(Honeſtum</hi> as they ſpeake) what is convenient will certainely prove a complaint: Both Religion and nature inſtruct us in this, Religion puts men on for holineſſe, as well as pulls men off from ſinfulneſſe; and nature hath ingrafted in it not onely <hi>(Abyſſus)</hi> depths of diſtaſts againſt apprehended evills, but alſo <hi>(Hiatus)</hi> vaſt deſires, for all throughly apprehended good: Neither will it receive ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:156756:20"/>
in the one without the other: Yea ordinary policy can diſcerne (in a Common-wealth) as great an aptneſſe to tumult where conveniencie is with held as there is to impatience, where miſery is felt: ſhall I adde one thing more? That in all publike changes and alterations, theſe ever goe in the thoughts of the vulgar (yea of all) Confident expectations that ſome other thing muſt ſucceed in the place of any thing that is removed, (eſpecially in matter of Religion where corruption is diſcerned on all ſides) the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and plantation of which, if publike authority doth not take in hand, you ſhall finde that ordinary heades will preſume to doe, the which what confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion it will make amongſt people, and future difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to your ſelves, I leave to your Religious wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes to conſider of.</p>
               <p>So then it is evident <hi>(de jure)</hi> that a ſowing ought to follow the breaking up; But yet any kinde of ſowing is not a ſufficient conſequent, the direction is given in the Text with a Caution, ſow, but ſow not among thornes.</p>
               <p>Interpreters abound in their opinions concerning <note place="margin">For the ſenſe of the words.</note> theſe thorns: By them <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> underſtands Idols (as entangling and piercing as the ſharpeſt of Briars and thornes) <hi>Origen</hi> and <hi>Hierom,</hi> by the thornes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand covetouſneſſe and the cares of the world (which likewiſe are ſcratching and wounding) others underſtand all our ſinfull corruptions', there are <hi>ſpinae in corde,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> thornes in our hearts, as well as in our Fields: and ſome underſtand by the thorns, mixtures of worſhip crept into the worſhip of God amongſt the <hi>Iewes</hi> (as <hi>Sanctius</hi> and others.) But with the favour of all theſe (and yet with ſubmiſſion)
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:156756:20"/>
I conjecture that theſe words <hi>(Sow not among Thornes)</hi> are a proverbiall ſpeech, and ſuggeſt onely this unto us, That as the <hi>Iewes</hi> were to breake downe what was evill in themſelves and the Church and State, ſo they were to ſet upon the doing of all good in private and publike, In ſuch a manner and order, as that their pains and endeavours might not come to nothing, but might prove effectuall and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſefull, be to ſome good purpoſe indeed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As an Husbandman who ſowes, will ſo ſow that hee may reape, and not looſe his ſeed and labour, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will not ſow among Thornes; For this were an improper worke, and would prove (in the event) utterly unprofitable: It is a thouſand to one if ever his ſeed comes up (for Thorns have a ſtealing, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing, and fruſtrating quality) or if it doth come up, yet it will be loſt, it cannot be gathered, there is no comming at it with ſithe or ſickle; Thornes have an hindering malignity, as well as a ſtifling power: From this expoſition, I obſerve onely this propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Namely.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label>
                  <hi>That all penitentiall and reforming worke must bee ſo managed and acted that it may not prove a vaine and fruitleſſe worke, but may come to be a ſucceſſefull and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table work:</hi> It muſt not be a ſowing among Thorns, but ſuch a ſowing which may in the iſſue produce an harveſt: for as good never a whit, as never the better.</p>
               <p>You read (in Scripture) of many Sowers.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The evill man did ſow Tares;</hi> wee have had (of <note place="margin">Foure ſorts of ſowers.</note> late) many ſuch Sowers, not onely profeſſed Prieſts and Jeſuites, but ſome alſo amongſt ourſelves who
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:156756:21"/>
have ſowen Popiſh, Arminian, Socinian, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious Tares.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The cunning man, and he ſowes diviſions and diſſentions; There have been (and ſtill are) too many who ſow diviſion twixt the King and the Parliament, twixt Miniſters and Miniſters, twixt Miniſters and people, twixt people and people.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The fooliſh man, and hee ſowes hee cares not what (in reſpect of the ſeed) nor where (in reſpect of the ſoyle) nor when (in reſpect of the time,) and ſo all is loſt and comes to nothing.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The wiſe man, who in his ſowing lookes to the ſeed that it bee good and cleane; and to the ſoyle that it bee prepared and right; and to the ſeaſon that it bee fit, upon which (through Gods bleſſing) the ſeed ſowen takes roote, proſpers, and proves an har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt.</p>
               <p>Of this I now ſpeake in the propoſition, which whither you limit it to a Repentance, that is perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, or extend it to a Reformation that is Nationall holds true in both, and the Text will beare both: The one and the other muſt bee ſo diſperſed, that it may not prove vaine and loſt, but effectuall and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſefull.</p>
               <p>Sirs! Though penitentiall workes rightly done are never without ſucceſſe and bleſſing, yet pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly penitentiall agents may ſo carry on theſe works (materially good) that they may never prove formal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and eventually good or beneficiall: and therefore you read in Scripture, that many prayings, and faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and ſolemne meetings, and teares, and other do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings have found no acceptation with God, nor wrought any ſubjective alterations in perſons, nor
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:156756:21"/>
change from miſery to mercy in a Nation; read the Prophets concerning the Jewes, and that will be teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony ſufficient.</p>
               <p>In ſixe caſes they prove (in the event) to bee nothing, but onely a ſowing amongſt thornes.</p>
               <p n="1">1. When they are but externall, not acted by any inward principles, the effects rather of art and parts then of the heart and grace: Shels, not kernells, teares of the eyes, but not teares of the heart, prayers of the lips, but not of the ſoule: Shadowes and pageants of Repentance, ſeeming to bee ſo to the eye of man, but not heart-workings which onely are interpreted to be true and ſolid to the eye of God:</p>
               <p>The Swanne in the Law was white in fethers yet reputed uncleane and unmeet for ſacrifice becauſe the skinne (under them) was black: Religious workings (you know) ſtand in Gods account according to the quality of the worke-man; the heart of whom is all in all for acceptance or rejection; God reputes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing done, which the heart doth not: Art may take man more than nature; but with God, the more art, the leſſe acceptance: A painted Repentance (which is onely externall) will doe our ſelves and the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as much good as a painted ſword, as a paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſtaffe, and as painted Fire; That will not cut, this will not helpe, the other will not heate, no more will a meerely externall Repentance pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent any judgements or obtaine any mercies.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When they are but partiall: A putting down of ſome ſinnes, and a keeping up of other ſinnes, will bee as vaine, as to cure the Palſey and yet to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:156756:22"/>
neglect the plague, or as to mend the pumpe and yet to neglect the leake; <hi>Iehu's</hi> Golden Calves made an end of him, though hee made an end of <hi>Baals</hi> Images and Prieſts; And ſo in the doing of good, it will come to nothing, though ſome good bee done and yet the beſt good is neglected; The Phariſees did many acts of Righteouſneſſe, but loſt them, and themſelves, becauſe they oppoſed and rejected <hi>Chriſt</hi> who was the chiefeſt and only Righteouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>There is (beloved) ſuch a naturall concatenation twixt all vices (and ſo there is amongſt vertues) That they (in a formall working) ever include an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall hatred, or an univerſall love: No man can be interpreted good, who is at defiance with any knowne particular good, nor doth hee ceaſe to bee wicked, who doth not hate and oppoſe every knowne evill: particular and excluſive actings in the one and in the other ſerve onely to the diſacceptance of the workes, and to the greater condemnation of the perſons.</p>
               <p>Though Imbecility ſhall never bee any preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to our works, yet ſubtiltie and partialitie ſhall.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When they are but circumſtantiall: though a multitude of leſſer evills bee cruſhed, if yet the greater are ſpared to ſurvive, This Reformation will prove like <hi>Sauls</hi> diſcretion with the <hi>Amale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kites,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Read, Ier. 48. 10.</note> who ſpared the fatteſt and deſtroyed the poor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, but he loſt the kingdome by it.</p>
               <p>Circumſtantiall reformations (I grant) are more eaſie and quicke, but thoſe which are moſt deepe, are ever moſt ſafe: a Cloath will ſtoppe up the wound as ſoone (and perhaps ſooner) then the plaiſter, but the plaiſter (which ſearcheth to the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:156756:22"/>
quicke) heales much better: If the Tree bee ſtarke naught (and good for no ſervice,) It is bettter to cut it downe to the Roote, then to hire men many dayes to out off the limbes.</p>
               <p>There are three great miſchiefes in all circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall and ſlight acts. One is, The greateſt cauſes of wrath are not met with.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
                  </label> A ſecond is, in a ſhort time all the plaſhed evills will (by a new influence from their rootes) ſprout up againe.</p>
               <p>And the third is, That when theſe evils once feele their ſtrength and regaine their opportunity, they will become more evill and miſchievous then ever: Hiſtories and experiences witneſſe enough of this Popery was hot in former Kings times, but when it got out the bit by the death of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, it burſt out with more burnings and flaming cruelty in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes.</p>
               <p n="4">4. When they are only Coactive: I meane ſuch actings unto which there is little or no concurrence of a judicious and active will, but are rather the ſparkles which are forced out by the colliſion of flints, elicited rather by the impreſſions of appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and urging evills: like <hi>Pharahos</hi> Obedience which was forced out of judgements, and nothing elſe.</p>
               <p>Marriners in a ſtorme are very pious, but then in a Calme turne as wicked as before: the <hi>Iewes</hi> in their ſtraites were as pliable as could bee deſired, they would part with any thing, and do any thing for <hi>God,</hi> but when the Sunne aroſe, this vaine Cloud and dew were gone and ſcatterd; If a Cloud of wrath bee it which puts us on to be and to do good, a few beames <note place="margin">Hoſea 6. 4.</note>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:156756:23"/>
of temporall ſafety will finde us flat, and ſtrangers againe; The Acts of men doe ſpring ſometimes from feare, and ſometimes from love, thoſe of feare may bee more ſtrong and ſtirring for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, (like a floud which runnes more violently then a River) but thoſe of love are moſt acceptable and conſtant: voluntary acts though ſometimes more ſlow, yet are at all times more ſucceſſefull: <hi>Iohn</hi> (in the Goſpell) ranne faſter then <hi>Peter,</hi> yet being at the Sepulcher, <hi>Peter</hi> went farther then <hi>Iohn, Iohn</hi> lookes downe, but <hi>Peter</hi> goes downe, an Arrow flies ſwifter, and a man walkes ſlower, yet a man may ſooner walke to the marke then the Arrow can hit it; Sirs! No private or publike work of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation will come to good, which is derived onely from a feare of evill, and not from a love of good, when the circumſtances of evill are of, the evill heart will ſhew it ſelfe evill again.</p>
               <p n="5">5. When they are hypocriticall and vaine-glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; done by our ſelves, and for our ſelves; It is a ſtrange thing to obſerve how the ſpirits of men are ballanced and mounted and keepe paralell with the ends which they propound unto themſelves! The Art and ſtrength and length of our workings are ever moulded in our owne aimes and reſpects: One man acts for God, another acts for himſelfe; the workes of the one are bleſt and proſper, the attempts of the other quickly languiſh and are blaſted; As vitious acts are under GODS curſe, ſo vaine-glorious acts are out of his bleſſing: Sinceritie, humble ſinceritie is that which gives life, findes acceptance, and is crowned with ſucceſſe.</p>
               <p>If a man in his religious performances of praying
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:156756:23"/>
and faſting, and humbling of himſelfe, ſhould ſeeke not God but himſelfe, as the Phariſees did, his vaine glory would purchaſe onely the applauſe of men and rejection with God; all his workes will bee loſt and come to nothing: <hi>Verily you have your reward ſaid Chriſt:</hi> a poore reward to have breath for breath! And ſo in publike attempts if you ſhould not entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeeke God, His Glory, His Truth, His Worſhip, but your ſelves, your worke will never proſper, It will reſt onely on your owne parts to act it, and on your own ſtrength to conſummate and perfect it, and what bleſſed iſſue can bee expected where weak man is left alone to bee the Author and finiſher of great actions?</p>
               <p n="6">6. Laſtly, when they are fickle and inconſtant; begun (perhaps) with ſome fervency, but then laid aſide by as much tepidity: An aguiſh zeale, hot in attempting, but cold in effecting; One day to act like penitents, and the next day to live like ſinners, one while humbling and praying, and after a while cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and ſwearing: Sometimes offering all our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and ſtrength for CHRIST and Religion, and <note place="margin">See Hoſea 6. 1, 4.</note> ſuddenly intent only to our owne delights and wayes, forgetting (like them who are much in complements) all our zeale and profeſſions: What a vanity will this prove? What harveſt will inſue when the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man will one houre ſow an handfull of ſeed, and a weeke after goe home and do nothing?</p>
               <p>It is obſerved in Nature, that many remiſſe acts (which have no proportion to effects) and ſome ſtrong acts ſoone remitted, will equally come to nothing: If there be to weake a ſtrength in the root, or if all the ſtrength ſhootes out at once, little or
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:156756:24"/>
no fruit will follow: yet this deceit cleaves much to mans heart that it wil either be conſtantly bad, or elſe inconſtantly good: It hath ſome degrees of heate to begin, but wants that prudence of patient endeavour and comming to finiſh and perfect: like him in the Goſpel who began to build, but did not make an end: Whereupon reſults a vanity and ſucceſſeleſneſſe to our workes; the ripeneſſe of which is betrayd many times more by our owne remiſſeneſſe, then by others oppoſitions: they ſticke and dye in the birth, becauſe wee continue not in our ſtrength, to helpe and bring them forth.</p>
               <p>I ſee that the time and your wearied patience call upon mee to haſten and finiſh: Give mee leave to make ſome uſefull application of all this, and then I have done; the application ſhall bee in this as in the former part a word.</p>
               <p>Firſt, To all of us, and then,</p>
               <p>Secondly, To you of great employment and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſervice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>1. To every one of us.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> WEE ſtand here (this day) before the Lord, and ſeeme to doe the worke of a ſolemne Faſt-day: We confeſſe Our ſinnes, Wee pray, Wee humble our ſelves, and profeſſe that wee will Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and reforme, and obey the Lord! Here hath been much ſeed ſowne (prayers are ſeed, Teares are ſeed, Sermons are ſeed.)</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:156756:24"/>But if all this ſowing ſhould bee but a ſowing amongſt thorns; if all this ſhould be ſo managed by us, that our prayers, that our confeſſions, that our hearings, that our reſolvings ſhould come to nothing, and prove nothing: If after once, twice, thrice, many humblings, we yet ſhould not be humbled; if after all the changes which befall our times, our hearts yet ſhould not be changed, but ſins remaine as ſtrong, and judgements remain as neare. If after all this, God ſhould not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled unto us, our tranſgreſſions ſhould not be pardoned, judgements ſhould not be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn, mercies ſhould not be ſent downe; what a bitter and ſad thing would this be for a man to periſh, though hee prayes, and to bee deſtroyed though he faſts, and a Nation to be made a curſe and an hiſſing, and a deſolation, after it hath ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to meet the Lord by ſolemne confeſſions and humiliations? To periſh in the ſhewes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance is a bitter periſhing.</p>
               <p>It was a ſad greeting which they found from Chriſt; Lord, ſay they, we have heard thee prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching in our Synagogues, we have eat and drunk in thy preſence; yet ſaith Chriſt unto them, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from me ye workers of iniquity, verily I know you not: So when we come to die, and then come to judgement, and ſay, Lord, we have heard thy Word, we have faſted, we have prayed, we have afflicted our bodies and ſoules; and yet Chriſt ſhall ſay, depart, I know you not, yee heard my Word indeed, but ye did not obey my Word; ye confeſſed your ſins, but yee never forſook your
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:156756:25"/>
ſins, ye gave on towards a little good, but ye never became good, you profeſſed obedience, but you never did care to walk in my wayes, and therefore all that you have done ſhall never doe you any good; would not this be a ſad and heavy anſwer to our ſelfe-deluded ſoules?</p>
               <p>Nay, put the caſe, that now after all our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings, the ſame judgement (or a worſe) ſhould befall us which befalls our poore Brethren in <hi>Ireland,</hi> that the ſword ſhould break forth among us, and all the unmercifull and ſudden calamities of warre ſhould beleaguer us, that in a moment the Goſpel ſhould bee baniſhed, our liberties ſhould be imbondaged, our eſtates ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted, our lands ſhould be diſpoſſeſſed, our houſes ſhould be burnt, our coffers ſhould be ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſack'd, our bodies ſhould be tortured, and our lives ſhould be threatned; Good Lord! would we ſay, is all our faſting and humbling come to this? we looked for good, and not for evill, wee looked for peace, and not for deſtruction; why? and the Lord might anſwer us, when did you faſt to me, and when did you pray to me? Indeed you prayed againſt judgements, but you would never leave your ſins, which (I told you often) would pull downe judgements: you would have had mercies, but I could never perſwade you to repent in good earneſt; you would truſt to vaine thoughts of your owne, you would never be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to purpoſe, you would ſow among thornes, and ſee now what ye get by it.</p>
               <p>O Chriſtian thinke ſeriouſly of theſe things!
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:156756:25"/>
God hath called to <hi>England,</hi> once, againe, often, a longer time, repent indeed, turne from your evill wayes indeed, be upright and holy indeed, walk with me once at length in truth; judgements have called, warnings have called, conſciences ſtill call, dangers ſtill call, feares ſtill call, the Miniſters of God (as the Prophets of old) ſtill call, and cry, and beſeech, and weepe; turne yet unto the Lord, turne not feignedly, but with all your hearts, ſow not among thornes; yet Lord! who believes our reports and calls? the Prophet is reputed a foole, and the Spirituall man mad, men will be ſinfull ſtill, they will (perhaps one of ten thouſand) bee ſeemingly penitent; and the iſſue (I feare) will bee this, <hi>the deſtruction of the tranſgreſſors and of the ſinners ſhall be together,</hi> Iſai. 1. 28. And <hi>while they be folden together as thornes, they ſhall be devoured as ſtubble fully dry,</hi> Nahum 1. 10</p>
               <p>But Sirs let us yet be perſwaded to repent, and to reforme our ſelves to purpoſe; if ever we pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to repent, or would repent to purpoſe, this is the time; all within us, all without us, all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, all at home beg it at our hearts: O that God would work all his works in us, that our ſelfe-reforming work may begin, goe on, hold out, and abound, that God may be reconciled to our ſelves, and this ſinfull land.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>2. To you of publique employment.</head>
               <p>MAny excellent works are fallen into your hands, ſome of them you have gone through
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:156756:26"/>
with already, and more (we are perſwaded) had received their ſeale, had not the excellency of your attempts raiſed againſt you, the enmity of manifold oppoſitions and contradictions; my humble and earneſt intreaty of you, is only this, let not thoſe remaining excellent works (if it bee poſſible, ſo much as in you lies) for ever ſtick in the birth; let them not die in meere intentions or propoſitions, but ſtrive to bring them unto their due and much deſired perfection; you have begun ſome things,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. About erronious Doctrines.</item>
                  <item>2. Againſt ſuperſtitious practices.</item>
                  <item>3. Againſt Idolatry, and ſeducing Prieſts and Jeſuits.</item>
                  <item>4. With notorious delinquents and offenders.</item>
                  <item>5. Againſt ſcandalous Miniſters and Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</item>
                  <item>6. For the ſetling of a faithfull and laborious Miniſtry.</item>
                  <item>7. For an honourable maintenance and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of it; (O never let us ſtand to the courteſie of the vulgar!)</item>
                  <item>8. For the eaſing of tender conſciences.</item>
                  <item>9. For the vindicating of the Lords day.</item>
                  <item>10. For the ſetling of all diſtractions, and hopes of a Church-Reformation according to the Word of God, againſt which malice it ſelfe cannot juſtly open its mouth.</item>
                  <item>11. For the ſuccouring and relieving of poore and diſtreſſed <hi>Ireland:</hi> Haſten all that you can, leſt it prove too late.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:156756:26"/>Now God forbid, that ſuch works as theſe ſhould ever fall to the ground, after ſo many yeers miſery, after ſo many thouſand prayers, after ſo many gracious overtures which you have made: let it not be ſaid of you in theſe works, as hee ſaid of his owne, <hi>Faciebam, non feci:</hi> he was doing of them, but they were never done. Take up your firſt thoughts, and engage your hearts and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and all your endeavours ſpeedily and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſefully to carry on (at leaſt) this one work of all works, a ſolid Reformation: Beleeve me, it is the work which will bring a bleſſing upon all your other works: peruſe that place well in <hi>Haggai</hi> 2. 18. <hi>Conſider now</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>from this day, even from the day that the foundation of the Lords Temple was laid, conſider it.</hi> (verſ. 19.) <hi>from this day will I bleſſe you.</hi> Now whereas <hi>Zerubba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel</hi> might reply, we would ſet to this work, but that we are afraid of warlike oppoſition; To this the Lord anſwers, in Verſe 22. and 23. <hi>I will over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the Throne of Kingdomes, and I will deſtroy the ſtrength of the Kingdomes of the Heathen; and I will overthrow the Charrets, and the Horſes, and the Riders: And I will take thee Zerubbabel my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, and I will make thee as a Signet, q. d.</hi> Look you to that work, and I will aſſuredly look to your perſons and ſafeties.</p>
               <p>Now that you may effectually carry on all theſe great works (and eſpecially that of Church-Reformation) ſo that all may be proſperous, and in the event come to ſomething; make uſe of two <note place="margin">Two Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> directions, which I humbly propound unto you.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:156756:27"/>Firſt ſtrip your ſelves of all the things which will weaken your hearts, and make your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours ſtill ſlow and fruitleſſe; therefore</p>
               <p>Firſt put off your ſinnes, or elſe they will put off your work: evill men are ſeldome apt for, or prove ſucceſſefull in good attempts: There is nothing which intricates our actions more than our ſinnes, which doe likewiſe enſnarle our ſouls; Enterpriſes ſet upon, either without God, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, are like arrowes ſhot up aloft, which never doe good, but many times doe much hurt. It is affirmed only of the godly man, That <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he doth, ſhall proſper, Pſal.</hi> 1. 3.</p>
               <p>Secondly, you muſt put off irregular feares: <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ecquid hoc in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>i age, corpus quidem occidere po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>unt, animam non poſſunt</hi> they were <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>inglius</hi> his laſt words.</note> you will never be exactly ſerviceable to God nor Religion, if you have any thing to loſe: <hi>ſhould ſuch a man as I flee?</hi> ſaid <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> Chap. 6. 11. guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty perſons who are contriving againſt the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of a Church and State, they may well feare; their conſciences may read terrours, and dangers, and loſſes to them. But perſons royally <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tibi adeſt nimia humilitas,</hi> ſaid <hi>Luther</hi> to <hi>Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitius.</hi>
                  </note> ſummoned, and piouſly employed for the right ſetling of a Church and Kingdome, as their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts are above all contumely, ſo their hearts <note place="margin">1 Pet 3. 13.</note> ſhould be above all fancies and feares: <hi>If yee</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Poene ſecurus ſpectator ſum &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> minaces &amp; ſcroces Papiſtas non hujus facio: ſi nos ruemus, ruet Chriſtus unâ ſcilicet ille regnator mundi,</hi> ſaid <hi>Luth. in lib. edit.</hi> 1549.</note> 
                  <hi>bee followers of that which is good, who is hee that will harme you.</hi> There can never bee any true danger nor loſſe by being good, or by doing good in our callings. The King of <hi>Poland,</hi> when his ſervant <hi>Zeliſlaus</hi> loſt his hand in his warres, ſent him inſtead thereof a golden hand: you ſhall never expend your ſtrength for God in
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:156756:27"/>
vaine, his ſervice is good, and reward ſure.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, you muſt put off favours: a publike man as hee ſhould have nothing to loſe, ſo hee ſhould have nothing to get: he ſhould be above <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Olim didici quid ſint munera,</hi> ſaid a worthy man.</note> all price or ſale: Truth and publike good ſhould only ſway and command him; he hath too im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent a ſpirit, whoſe ſervices (like the diall) muſt be ſet only by the Sunne, who ſaith to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement and reſpect, as <hi>Tiberius</hi> once anſwered <hi>Iuſtinus</hi> (though upon a better ground and end) <hi>Si tu volueris, Ego ſum; Si tu non vis, ego non ſum;</hi> I am only thy clay and wax. It was a brave com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of <hi>Luther</hi> (though not intended by that Cardinall who ſpake it) That German Beaſt cares not for gold. And <hi>Henry,</hi> afterwards Duke <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Anno.</hi> 1539.</note> of <hi>Saxony</hi> rather adventured the hopes of the Dukedome, than that he would be bound not to change and reforme a corrupt Religion.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, you muſt put off prejudices: If the great work of Church-Reformation ſeemes to any of you either fordid and contemptible, or hopeleſſe and impoſſible, or needleſſe and idle, or unſeaſonable and inconvenient; you will ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be formall in attempts, or ſubtle to entan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, or profeſſedly oppoſite to cruſh the work, and bring it to nothing; But yet Worthies of our Iſrael, know, that Reformation is</p>
               <p>An Honourable work: It is a work fit for a <note place="margin">Honourable to you, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable to the Church, which the more pure it is, the more excellent it is.</note> God, fit for the greateſt Monarchs on earth; and the greateſt Reformers in Religion have attained thereby to the greateſt ſplendor and glory, as <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah, Iehoſophat, Ioſiah,</hi> King <hi>Edward,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:156756:28"/>A poſſible work: Though there be many knots, and blocks, and rubs, and alarums; yet doe you unanimouſly and ſtrenuouſly act, act and the work is done; <hi>poſſunt</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>quia poſſe videntur:</hi> the Hiſtorians aſcribe moſt of King <hi>Alexanders</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe to his courage, there was nothing he attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but hee conceived it might bee done. All works for God are both honourable and fecible: As <hi>Tertullian,</hi> in comparing the Reſurrection with the Creation, ſaid it was more eaſie <hi>reficere quam facere,</hi> to make up the body againe, than ſimply to make it to be; that ſame holds true in this caſe, it is more eaſie to reforme than to forme a Church; as the work is eaſier to cure a diſeaſed body, than to enliven a dead body.</p>
               <p>A needfull work: A Reformation is needfull when a Church is like to be poyſoned with er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, or to be rent with contrariety of opinions, or is ſick with manifold corruptions. This is our condition, and beſides all this, we ſee great judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments hanging over us, which have befallen other Churches: were it not better to reforme before judgements, than under them? who can tell but it may be an effectuall meanes to prevent them?</p>
               <p>Laſtly, it is a ſeaſonable work: If you judge it a fit ſeaſon for our Church to be humbled, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly then it is a fit ſeaſon for it to be reformed: that which puts us upon the one, directs us alſo to the other; but I paſſe on.</p>
               <p>Secondly, If you would carry on this work for good, then you muſt get into your hearts,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:156756:28"/>
and cheriſh in your thoughts all thoſe things which will quicken you to the perfecting of ſuch a work.</p>
               <p>Firſt, you muſt labour to poſſeſſe your hearts with thoſe active, induſtrious, and unwearied gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ſelfe-deniall, of ardent love of God, of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed zeale for his glory, and of ſublime faith, which will raiſe your ſpirits above all difficulties and oppoſitions, above all clouds and ſeas: were men thus qualified, they would then count no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing too deare, or too much for God, but would moſt cheerefully ſpend and be ſpent for him, they would lend all their honours, places, gifts, abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, all to the ſervice of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>And ſecondly, you muſt cheriſh quickning thoughts: I will make bold to propound ſome unto you, only to adde, at leaſt, to what you have, and doe know already.</p>
               <p>Firſt, minde much the dignity of the work, and minde little the malignity of the oppoſers: when the Temple was to bee re-built, you know what oppoſition <hi>Sanballat,</hi> and <hi>Tobiah,</hi> and others made, what accuſations, what letters, what attempts, and devices againſt <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> and the reſt; but they minded the work of the Temple the more, their eyes were upon God and his ſervice: So when <hi>Luther</hi> began the Reformation in <hi>Germany,</hi> you read that the Pope and his Cardinalls, and their currs preſently opened their foule mouthes, crying out, that he was <hi>(mendax, perfidus, apoſtata, tuba</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide</hi> Mel. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>ia vita</hi> Lutheri <hi>pag.</hi> 144 145.</note> 
                  <hi>rebellionis, quod omnia quae de moliminibus Papae ſcripſiſſet, ficta erant &amp; ementita &amp;c.)</hi> a liar, perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:156756:29"/>
an Apoſtate, a trumpet of rebellion and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; and that all which hee charged on the Pope, were but his owne vaine ſurmiſes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices: yet <hi>Luther</hi> went on with the work, and maugre all contradiction, prevailed and proſpered: The like we read in our owne Chronicles, when King <hi>Edward</hi> ſet upon Reformation, what ſcorns, deriſions, oppoſitions, ſides, tumults encountred it by the Friars, and the Popiſh party; yet hee kept on the work, and greatly proſpered in it: the excellency of the work, and a conſciouſneſſe of his duty, and confidence in God, made his Arke to ſwim upon all thoſe raging waters.</p>
               <p>Secondly, minde your encouragements more, and all diſcouragements leſſe: <hi>Tolle Coelum, &amp;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Chriſt did once die for ſinners, but he ever reigns ſor truth: ſo <hi>Luth.</hi> in an Epiſtle to <hi>Melanchion.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>nullus ero,</hi> ſaid <hi>Empedocles</hi> once: Take away hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and I am no body; all ſerenity comes from above us, the damps riſe from that which ſhould be under our feet. Worthy Sirs, as the Prophets charriots with him were more than the charriots of the adverſaries againſt him, ſo I may ſay, there are more with you (being in Gods work) than can be againſt you: In a good work you have a God commanding (as once to <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> chap. 1. 9. <note place="margin">See Iudges 6. 12, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Have not I commanded thee? be ſtrong and of a good courage;)</hi> and a God protecting you (as in the ſame place, <hi>the Lord thy God is with thee whitherſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thou goeſt,)</hi> and a God promiſing to bleſſe <note place="margin">Read Eſay 41. 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, &amp;c.</note> and reward you: me thinks all this ſhould lift up your hearts, and ſtrengthen them much. I have read a ſtory of one <hi>Iulius Pflugius,</hi> who had been employed by the Emperor, but was much wronged
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:156756:29"/>
and injured by the Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> of which complaining, <hi>Caeſar</hi> returned him this anſwer, have a little patience, <hi>Tua cauſa erit mea cauſa,</hi> thy cauſe and condition ſhall be mine owne, and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cauſa ut ſit magna, magnus eſt actor &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ejus, neque enim noſtra eſt:</hi> Luth. Melan.</note> this was heartning enough; God ſaith the ſame to you, make you the ſame in livening uſe of it; weakneſſe (ſaid he in <hi>Sophocles)</hi> is ſtrong enough if God will fight.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, minde the ſtrength which you have by prayers, more than the words that are againſt you and evill minded men; the language of wicked men is but an empty breath, it may declare malice, but doth not aſſure us of power, but the language of prayer is a mighty &amp; doing breath, it can ſhake Heaven and Earth; the prayer of one good man hath wrought wonders, it hath conquered God, and Men, and Devils: wicked adverſaries may ſet men to work, but prayer ſets a God to work. And you (Right Honourable) you have millions of prayers almoſt every day ſent up to Heaven for you: It cannot be, ſaid Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> to <hi>Monica,</hi> that a childe of ſo many teares and prayers ſhould periſh; ſo ſay I, it cannot be, that ſuch Worthies, who are every day compaſſed about with ſo many prayers, ſhould miſcarry; you have the prayers of three Kingdomes for you, and I am perſwaded alſo, the prayers of all the people of God through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole world.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, minde the excellency of the iſſue, and not the difficulty of the progreſſe: We ſay in Philoſophy that <hi>Finis dat amabilitatem &amp; vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutem;</hi> the end maketh the work amiable, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:156756:30"/>
gives ſtrength to the workman. This I obſerve, that great and choice ſervices are more difficult when they are in agitation, than when they are in action, more when we are contriving of them, than when we are doing them; but though they be difficult to be wrought, yet when they are fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed they are glorious and excellent: The Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple was long in building, but when it was finiſhed, there was not the like in all the world, for it was filled with the glory of the Lord from the Mercy-Seat. O what a glory unto our good God, what a beauty to our Church, what an honour to our Nation, what a ſatisfaction to all pious hearts, what a ſafety to this Land, what an influence to all the Churches of Chriſt will this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation prove if it could be once effectually wrought by Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and your ſucceſſefull endeavours.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
